<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: work | Riot Control (test)]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.riot-control.net/categories/work/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.riot-control.net/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-10T15:37:12+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.riot-control.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[REWORK &amp; REMOTE: Office Not Required]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.riot-control.net/2014/04/21/rework-and-remote/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-21T21:01:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.riot-control.net/2014/04/21/rework-and-remote</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
<img style="border-style:solid;border-color:black;" src="/images/rework.jpg" height="300px" width="200px"/>

<img style="border-style:solid;border-color:red;" src="/images/remote.png" height="300px" width="200px"/>
</p>


<p>Remember the <strong>Godfather</strong> movies? I bet you&rsquo;ve seen them before. (If you haven&rsquo;t, stop reading right now and go watch them. Just kidding.)</p>

<p>There are 3 Godfather movies: Part I, Part II and Part III. Let&rsquo;s just focus on Part I and Part II. Which one did you like the most? Part I? It&rsquo;s a classic, great movie. Do you think Part II is better? I know some people who do. It&rsquo;s also awesome. Both are great movies, there&rsquo;s no question about that.</p>

<p>The same happens with these two <strong>life changing books</strong>: REWORK and REMOTE. Both of them are so good it&rsquo;s hard to say which one is better.</p>

<p>These books have completely changed the way I work and how I manage to keep a <strong>healthy work-life balance</strong>.</p>

<p>Let me just give you an idea of what they talk about. Then, go read them and <strong>change your life forever</strong>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><strong>REWORK</strong> and <strong>REMOTE</strong> were written by <strong>Jason Fried</strong> and <strong>DHH</strong> from <strong>37signals/Basecamp</strong>.
REWORK focuses on how you can become a better worker. REMOTE is all about working outside the office and all the benefits and dangers that come with it. So, how can you become more productive?</p>

<p>For example, most people go to the office everyday. But they don&rsquo;t get that much work done. Their day is shredded into tiny moments. 10 minutes here, 20 minutes there. The office is full of <strong>interruptions</strong>. Try working outside the office for one day and see how much work you get done.</p>

<p>Since I&rsquo;m talking about the office, how about working from 9am-5pm? I mean, we&rsquo;re all supposed to be productive at the same time for 8 hours? What if somebody works better from 12pm-8pm? You should <strong>focus on the work</strong> you have to do, not at what time you do it. Some people get work done at offices really early in the morning or late in the afternoon when nobody&rsquo;s there to distract them. Seriously, <strong>it&rsquo;s the work that matters</strong>, not the clock.</p>

<p>Now, how about having flexible workdays outside the office? Most managers will come up with this excuse: &ldquo;If I can’t see them, how do I know they’re working?&rdquo;. <strong>Remote work is all about trust</strong>. Treat your employees like adults and you’ll be the manager. Treat them like children and you’ll be the babysitter. Some managers trust their employees, others like to control them.</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>&ldquo;To successfully work with other people, you have to trust each other. A big part of this is trusting people to get their work done wherever they are, without supervision.&rdquo; &ndash; Richard Branson</strong></p></blockquote>

<p>Another excuse managers come up with to avoid remote work is: &ldquo;People’s homes are full of distractions&rdquo;. Yes they are. And so are offices. The difference? At home you have <strong>voluntary distractions</strong>. It&rsquo;s up to you to stop working and go watch TV. If you’re tempted by home distractions, maybe your work isn’t motivating and meaningful. On the other hand, at the office you have <strong>involuntary distractions</strong> (coworkers, managers, meetings, etc.).</p>

<p><strong>Meetings and Managers</strong> are the main reasons work doesn’t get done at the office (Jason and David call them the <strong>M&amp;M&rsquo;s</strong>). Meetings are major distractions. Meetings should be like salt &ndash; sprinkled carefully to enhance a dish, not poured recklessly over every forkful. Too much salt destroys a dish. <strong>Too many meetings can destroy morale and motivation</strong>. Also, a 1 hour meeting with 5 people is actually a 5 hour meeting. A 1 hour meeting with 5 people means less 5 hours of productivity, not less 1 hour.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s sum it up:</p>

<ul>
<li>Work outside the office</li>
<li>Focus on the work, not the clock</li>
<li>Beware of the M&amp;M&rsquo;s</li>
</ul>


<blockquote><p><strong>&ldquo;The big transition with distributed workforce is going from synchronous to asynchronous collaboration. Not only do we not have to be in the same spot to work together, we also don’t have to work at the same time to work together.&rdquo; &ndash; Jason Fried &amp; David Heinemeier Hansson</strong></p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
